# 哈喽 大家好
Hello, everybody.
# 今天我们弄来昨天搬来这个石磨
Today we use this mill that we moved yesterday.
# 今天磨点豆花来吃 招待一下我们的好朋友 李智
Let's mill some soybeans for our good friend, Li Zhi.
# 他的父亲是我们富顺豆花的大师刘锡禄的徒弟
His father is disciple of the Fushun Douhua master, Liu Xilu.
# 然后李智相当于是我们这个（刘锡禄)第三代传承人吧
So Li Zhi is the third generation successor of Liu Xilu.
# 今天我们做一个豆花
Today we're making a Douhua.
# 包括我们前面拍的豆花里面的这个工具
Featuring those tools from the video we shot earlier.
# 还有一些技术的一些东西
And some of the technical stuff.
# 全部是由李智为我们提供更详细的技术支持
All supported by Li Zhi.
# 所以今天为了答谢他我们就推一个豆花 是吧
So to thank him today, we'll make Douhua for him.
# 招待一下我的好朋友李智
To better treat my good friend Li Zhi.
# 这个豆子已经泡了四五个小时了噶
These beans have been soaked for four or five hours?
# 嗯 没得 我7点过泡的
Hmm, no, I soaked them at about 7:00am.
# 7点过我看 （现在)10点半了
About 7:00am. It's 10:30am now.
# 7点过10分泡的
It was 10 minutes past 7:00am.
# 10点半了
It's 10:30am now
# 没得问题的撒
It's no problem.
# 李老师
Mr. Li.
# 推得不嘛 豆花
Is that good to go?
# 推也推得
It should be okay.
# 推也推得 再泡会也可以 要的推嘛
Should be alright, longer soaking is also fine... just do it!
# 要的
Yes.
# 好 四伯爷帮我加嘛
Okay, Uncle, help me.
# 要的嘛 我站哪个位置安 这边噶
Yes, where do I stand? Here.
# 拿这个桶接
Use this bucket.
# 四伯爷好大的岁数哦
How old are you, Uncle?
# 62噶
# 哦 这种就是传家宝了
Oh, you are a family treasure.
# 家有一老如有一宝
Having an elder is like a treasure!
# 一脚一手
Every step, every movement.
# 嗯 一手一脚
Yeah, every movement and every step.
# 都不能够马虎要认真对待这个事情
You can't be sloppy about making Douhua. You have to take this seriously.
# 第一个要对得起这个技术
The first, has to be responsible for the heritage.
# 第二个要对得起这个食客
The second, has to be responsible for the customer.
# 人家出钱吃你这碗豆花
He or she's paying you for a bowl of Douhua.
# 是 我们这个豆花
Yes, this Douhua.
# 我做了这么多次了
I've done this so many times.
# 我推了有一两百斤黄豆了
I've ground a couple hundred kilos of soybeans.
# 感觉还是要用石磨推的没有那个粗的渣
I still feel the soy milk from a stone mill is finer, there is no coarse residue.
# 用机器打的始终它煮出来的渣颜色都有点不对
If it's done by a machine, the color of the pulp always feels a bit wrong.
# 这是因为石磨碾得比较充分一点是不
That's because the milling process is more thorough by using stone.
# 更均匀 就是说它是这个概念
It's more uniform. That's the concept.
# 这种石磨推出来的豆花碾压的速度
The speed of the mill stone.
# 碾压的那种程度
The level of milling.
# 碾压的那种重量或者碾压的细致程度的话
The weight to mill, or the granularity of the milling...
# 它能够保持这个豆子原有的风味
It maintains the original flavor of the soy.
# 不破坏它
Without destroying it.
# 它不得破坏那个豆子原有的豆香味
It's not going to ruin that bean's original aroma.
# 对 我也发现一个问题
Yeah, I found a problem too.
# 机器打的转速太高了
The machine is revving too high.
# 它那个豆子容易发烫
The soy becomes hot easily.
# 磨的时候发热的话那个蛋白质没得好好的噶
The protein won't be good if it's hot when you mill it.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 石磨磨的就不得破坏它
Stone mills won't have the problem.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 我又来整2哈嘛
Let me do it.
# 李老师 你来加哈嘛
Mr. Li, you add the soy.
# 来嘛来嘛
Come here.
# 你加哈豆子 我加豆子我要撞到杆杆
You add the soy, I'll hit the pole if I am adding the soy.
# 那这样子就比较对
That's more like it.
# 啊
Right
# 哎呦
Oops...
# 诶 四伯爷
Haa, Uncle.
# 这咋子的哦
What's the problem?
# 稍微往上面抬一点的
Lift it a little bit.
# 不是的 高了点 我就矮点
It's taller. I'm shorter.
# 哦 这就是对的
Oh, that's right.
# 拉重一点 拉快一点
Pull harder. Pull faster.
# 免得它漫出来
Prevent it from spilling out.
# 尝哈看
Try it.
# 冰糖整点都
Add some white rock sugar.
# 很香
Smells good.
# 香
Good!
# 人家点得好的 慢慢点的豆花
He did it well. Very patient when salting the Tofu.
# 一样的豆子
The same amount of beans.
# 啊
Yeah.
# 比如三斤豆子人家也是三斤豆子
Like using the same three jin of beans for example.
# 就比你点的豆花多得多
He can produce more "Douhua" than you did.
# 李老师你是看得后面还是看的前面哦
Mr. Li, are you looking at the back or the front?
# 看锅面上嘛
The surface.
# 看锅面上
Look at the surface.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 我有好几回就是点到这个样子我就停了
For a couple of times, I stopped salting at this point.
# 你的盐卤水就不够撒
You didn't add enough brine.
# 就没有点 这个出来就是浑的
It was not completed, so it seemed muddy.
# 像这个时候就不管它了噶
So we can stop at this point?
# 嗯 这样可以了
Yeah, now is finished.
# 好了 现在我们这个都OK了
Okay, now we're all good with this one.
# 现在就是明显感觉到这个
It seems obvious right now that
# 絮状的这个小豆腐已经凝固了
the little "Douhua" has congealed.
# 再往下点的话就成了豆腐了噶
Any further down and it would be tofu.
# 就老了
It will get too firm.
# 就是把它整老了就变成豆腐了
You know, when it gets firm, it turns into tofu.
# 不安
Not good.
# 都老了
It's too firm.
# 做豆腐都老了
It's too firm even for tofu.
# 还要一会儿呀
It'll take a while.
# 还没有凝固的嘛
It's not congealed yet.
# 这个豆花又是哪个发明的安
Who invented "Douhua"?
# 豆花的由来就是
The origin of "Douhua" is that
# 先有豆腐
Tofu was invented first.
# 啊 先有豆腐
Ah, tofu first.
# 因为以前的盐工
Because of the salt-well workers in the past.
# 大部分就是吃豆腐
Mostly they just ate tofu.
# 因为吃肉吃不起
Because they couldn't afford to eat meat.
# 小菜一年四季又不一定有那么多小菜 没见到啥子
You don't always have that many vegetables all year round.
# 大部分都吃豆腐 有些安就饿得发慌
Most of them ate just tofu, some of them got hungry easily.
# 在锅里还没成型的时候就舀来吃
So they scoop the unfirmed Tofu up and ate it while it was still in the wok.
# 因为他饿了来等不及了 他觉得这个豆花要比豆腐好吃
Because they were hungry and couldn't wait. They thought the "Douhua" were better than the tofu.
# 豆花要比豆腐好吃
Douhua is better than tofu.
# 他觉得这个嫩豆花 比如说这个样子就舀来吃了
They scooped out the soft "Douhua", for example, just looked like this.
# 他这样子舀来吃还多好吃
They found It was so delicious when he ate it like this.
# 比豆腐好吃
It's better than tofu.
# 哪边开了就往哪边移
Push it to the side when it's boiled.
# 你舀还要转哈圈圈
You have to scoop like spinning a circle.
# 我刚开始
I just started.
# 稍微嫩点
A little tender.
# 我刚开始舀都是按下去就把它按坏了
I just started scooping it all down and broke it.
# 来嘛
Come on.
# 坐 李老师 坐这儿
Take a seat, Mr. Li. Please sit here.
# 四伯爷尝哈这个豆花
Uncle, try this "Douhua".
# 好
Very nice.
# 爸爸
Dad!
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 好
Okay.
# 这个给你
Here you go.
# 好 叫妈妈吃饭了
Okay, go and call mommy for lunch.
# 这个蘸水还多安逸
It's a nice dip.
# 还是要传统手艺的这个豆花和蘸水才好吃
It's better to have "Douhua" and dip made in the traditional way.
# 现代技术的做出来有点（没那么好吃）
Modern technology makes it a little (less delicious).
# 你看这个豆花就不苦噶这个豆花
Look at this "Douhua", it does not taste bitter.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 这顿豆花是我吃过最好吃的豆花了
This "Douhua" is the best I've ever had.
# 真的嘛假的哦
Seriously?
# 真的
Indeed.
# 真的好吃
It's really good.
# 很嫩 而且做得真的太好吃了
It's tender and it's really delicious.
# 你不看哈 是哪个做的
Don't you see which one made it?
# 就是
Exactly.
# 就是想说这句话 我害怕等会说我（拍马屁）
That's what I'm trying to say. I'm afraid I'll be called out flattering.
# 确实这个豆花好吃
It's indeed that the "Douhua" is delicious.
# 真的好吃
It's really good.
# 我们李老师指导了我们做了一次
Our teacher, Mr. Li, instructed us to make it this time.
# 但是怎么说呢
But how do I put it?
# 中间还是靠我个人去摸索里面的一些
I still have to figure out some of the skills myself.
# 很细微的那种经验
A very subtle kind of experience.
# 凡是人家教你只能把你领进门
If someone teaches you, they can only guide you in.
# 真正要靠自己去把它摸透 还是要经过实践
It's really up to you to figure it out. It needs practice.
# 不断的实践
Continuous practice
# 就是我教你一百次你一次不实践没有用的
Even if I've taught you a hundred times, it is of no use if you don't practice
# 对吧
Agree?
# 嗯
Yeah